this video currently has over 21 million
views on YouTube and the reason so many
Traders found that video valuable is
because I poured a ton of time and
effort to ensure that by the end of that
video Traders knew everything they
needed to know about technical analysis
in this video I'm doing the same exact
thing for Price action so throughout the
next 50 minutes you are going to learn
everything from the complete basics of
price action to a full price action
trading system that I've utilize to pull
profits out of the market for over 8
years so if you are a beginner or
struggling Trader that's currently
having trouble with any part of price
action trading or that currently doesn't
have a price action trading system and
trading plan then this video is made for
you so if you're ready to learn
everything you need to know about price
action over the next 50 minutes sit back
relax and I'll be right back after the
intro and a swim
[Music]
welcome back and let's go aad and get
started with what is price action
trading price action trading is a
technique that allows traders to trade
not based on indicators but instead
based on previous and current price
movements and the way we make money by
trading based on price action is by
taking a look at different price action
factors factors such as Trend reversals
major levels of structure breakouts
Candlestick patterns chart patterns and
so much more but all of these factors
are utilized and combined in order to
help us make more informed and more
accurate trading decisions so now I'm
going to be diving into each of these
price action factors and explaining them
to you in detail so that you can not
only spot them in your own trading but
utilize them to make more accurate
trading decisions and a little later in
the video I'm also going to be showing
you an entire rules-based price action
trading strategy so let's go ahead and
get started with lesson number
[Music]
one I have a very simple set of rules
that helps me to identify trending
markets visualizing a trending Market is
very easy an uptrend is higher highs and
higher lows a downtrend is lower lows
and lower Highs but for those of you who
are beginner and struggling Traders I
understand that it can be daunting to
look at a chart and try to determine
what the trend is so with that being the
case let me explain my exact rules for
identifying Trend right now the first
step in ident ifying a trending Market
is understanding major swing highs and
lows because these are what we're going
to use to determine if price is in fact
continuing in Trend or starting to
reverse so when identifying Trend I
always pick a starting point it's going
to be right here in this case and this
starting point has a push higher to a
new swing High how do I know this is a
new swing High well because a pullback
happened right after it now for a
pullback I have very specific rules I
want to see two opposite color candles
for a pullback to exist so if we're in
an uptrend I want to see at least two
red candles they don't have to be
consecutive but they do have to be
larger red candles I don't want to see
two little dogey red candles that
wouldn't count as a pullback but these
two candles would count as a pullback
for me after that pullback occurs I want
to see price break into new Highs at
this point I can identify two different
things and that is Major swing highs and
lows so at first we have our pushup from
here to our new swing High we then have
a pullback right here's the lowest point
of that pullback and we have a break and
close above our previous swing High when
this happens I just take a horizontal
line and I put it at the lowest point of
our previous pullback before the
breaking close into new structure highs
so we need to see this one two three
move meaning a move up a pullback and
then a breaking close above the swing
high that was previously created at the
point that we have this pullback and we
have a breaking close above the swing
High we can point out our major swing
low the reason this is important in
identifying trend is that this Market is
considered to be in an uptrend unless a
candle closes below this previous swing
low which again is the lowest point in
the previous pullback so I continue
doing this by putting a horizontal line
at our swing High which is our major
swing High which is where our pullback
started and during this pullback as long
as we stay above this previous swing low
and we don't have a candle that closes
below it we can actually have a wick
come down here that's completely fine I
just don't want to see a close below
this area as long as that close below
doesn't happen I'm still considering
this Market to be in an uptrend and this
process just continues as we go higher
this move here we go from the low of our
pullback we break and close above that
right here so now I'm looking at this as
our major swing High because we start
our pullback from here and I'm looking
at this as our major swing low what this
means is that during this pullback as
long as price does not come down and
close below the lowest low of the
previous pullback we're still considered
to be in an uptrend so even if we have
consolidation here and we have price
doing crazy stuff between this swing
high and this swing low I'm still
considering this Market in an uptrend
unless we break and close below the
previous major swing low let's continue
the process to make sure you have a good
handle on it as we push higher and we
close above this swing High where do I
move my major swing low I can't move
this until our previous high is broken
but at this point when that previous
high is broken I'm looking at my major
swing low as being the lowest low of the
pullback before the breaking close above
the previous swing high so at this point
what is this telling me this is telling
me that as long as we don't close below
our previous pull pull back before the
breaking close Above This high that we
are still in an uptrend and this is
super important for you to understand
because we're going to be utilizing this
as we move forward in every other aspect
of our price action trading so be sure
that you are paying attention as we
continue this process after we have this
pullback starting I would be moving my
major swing high up to here what do I
want to see I want to see at least two
not dogee red candles and we have these
three red candles that's when I would
actually be moving moving that line up
to my new major swing high and when this
swing High breaks after this pullback
that does not in fact closed below my
previous pullback so we're still in what
still in an uptrend here then we break
and close above this swing high if we
had a higher pullback a higher swing low
here I would be moving this line up but
as you can see we have an equal swing
low here so this line stays exactly
where it is but we do have a new swing
High major swing High
once we start this pullback and
considering where Price is Right now
what do you think we should be doing
well we can't consider this a new swing
High yet because we don't have two red
candles in the pullback that's the only
time we can consider a new swing high
but we have gotten what we've gotten a
close above our previous swing high with
this candle so with that being the case
I can actually take my horizontal line
and move it up to the lowest point of
this pullback and now with that being
the case what does that mean that means
that I'm still considering this Market
in an uptrend unless price pulls back
and eventually closes below this area as
long as that doesn't happen we can see
anything in between this high and this
low price can consolidate move back and
forth I am still considering price to be
in an uptrend unless we close below the
lowest point of the previous pullback
and those are the most objective rules I
have for identifying Trend and an
uptrend let's quickly go over a
downtrend example it's going to be
nearly the same thing just flipped
upside down let's take a look at that
right now so here we have a downtrend we
have our starting point followed by our
one two three move which is just this
move down followed by a pullback and a
breaking close below that previous major
swing low right here we also have the
start of a pullback looking right here
so with this being the case what can we
do based on what you've learned so far
at this point we can point out our major
swing low and our major swing High what
does this mean this means that we are
still considering this Market to be in a
downtrend unless we get a candle that
comes up and closes Above This previous
major swing high as long as that does
not happen we can see anything happen in
between and we're still considering this
Market to be in a downtrend unless we
get that close Above This level right
here so with that being the case let's
push our black Black Box forward and as
you can see after our pullback we get up
to a swing High we then do what we break
and close below our previous swing low
what this allows me to do considering
that we've seen the start of this
pullback is I can now identify my new
major swing low as well as my new major
swing high that again price cannot break
for us to continue in this downtrend if
price does break this area and close
above it with a candle then I'm no
longer considering this a downtrend so
with that being the case let's see what
price did price continued this pullback
up to this point then pushed down and
closed below our previous swing low
again and considering that we've started
our pullback already right here this
allows us to yet again push our swing
low down to this new major swing low and
this has now become our major swing High
because it's the top of the pullback
before the breaking close below the
previous swing low next up we get
another pullback that ends right here
followed by another breaking close below
this level so yet again we can move our
lines down new swing low new major swing
high right here and as long as a candle
doesn't close above this area we're
still in a downtrend I know what you're
thinking though Stephen what if a candle
does close above our previous major
swing High well that's what we're going
to dive into right
[Music]
now reversals and trend are intertwined
and they are both a major part of price
action trading what you've learned so
far about trend is going to make it
super easy for you to be able to spot
potential reversals so I'm going to go
through this section rather quickly but
let's go ahead and take a look at the
exact rules I utilize in order to spot
reversals in any Market first we're
taking a look at a bullish reversal we
have price that has been in what type of
trend as you can see from our major
swing highs and lows that we have
pointed out price here on the New
Zealand dollar has been in a downtrend a
reversal is simply when the trend fails
and what I mean by the trend fails is
that instead of creating a lower high
and continuing in Trend instead in a
reversal scenario price comes up and
closes above our previous major swing
high that is a warning sign that prices
could very well start to Trend upwards
now instead of the previous downtrend
that prices were just in and the reason
this is the case is because now the
sentiment of this Market has completely
changed we've went from consistently
making lower lows and lower highs to now
making a higher high compared to the
previous swing High meaning a lot more
buyers are stepping into this market so
with that being the case and with the
trend failing here that sets us up for a
possible reversal opportunity as prices
do in fact head higher here on the
Canada Swiss we're going to take a look
at a bearish reversal so on this
currency pair you can see that we have
new highs new higher lows new higher
High new higher low new higher high
let's go back to trend for a second
right now we have our major swing high
and our major swing low when this trend
fails which means if price closes below
our major swing low before pushing up
and reaching new higher highs that is
when we are looking for possible
reversal trades and we're going to talk
about how we look for those trades later
on when we discuss more price action
factors but let's go ahead and take a
look here at price and what it does as
soon as we get this close below with
this big red candle our previous
pullback in our uptrend our previous
major swing low as soon as that happens
it puts us on red alert for possible
reversal trades and what does the market
do we get a pullback into that exact
level and we get a complete reversal out
of price so with what you learned in the
previous about trending markets spotting
reversals is extremely simple it is just
when those trending rules fail now that
you have Trend and reversals down let's
move on to the next
[Music]
lesson Trends and reversals are how we
pick the direction that we want to trade
in any Market but after picking the
direction it's important to pick the
most accurate and the most profitable
area to place those trades in for
example in an uptrend we know we want to
buy but where do we want to place that
Buy trade in a downtrend where do we
want to place that sell trade and in a
reversing Market what's the most
profitable area for us to place a trade
in in order to capture that reversal
this is where major levels of structure
come into play let's get started now
with Trend continuation major levels of
structure we're going to start out with
a bullish example on the screen right
now where price is based on what you've
learned where is the latest major swing
level that would be this level right
here so all I do when figuring out if I
have a major level of structure for a
bullish Trend that I can possibly trade
around is point out that last major
swing high and when we're looking at
structure levels they're never going to
be just a line on the chart they're
always zones so what I want to do is
create a Zone here in this area and this
is going to be that major level of
structure but the criteria that it has
to meet is that not only for a trend
continuation major level of structure
not only do need this level to be the
previous major swing high that was
broken in our Trend this level also has
to be tested multiple times looking left
so we have to scroll the chart back in
this case and ask ourselves has this
level been tested multiple times that
answer is yes as long as those two
qualifications are met then I have a
major structure level for Trend
continuation trades what that means is
now that I've pointed that out and now
that I know I do have this major level
of structure here while we're in this
uptrend what I'm going to be be waiting
on for possible trades it's just a pull
back into this area and throughout the
next sections we'll talk more about
entry reasons but if we click play here
on this chart you'll see that price did
in fact come right to that level of
structure and then took off to the
upside so these are the levels that
we're going to be looking at to trade in
and this is how we're going to spot out
those major levels of structure in
uptrends again the trend is telling us
the direction we want to trade these
major levels of structure are telling us
where we want to be looking for those
trading opportunities at now let's take
a look at a bearish trend continuation
zone so on the screen right now you can
see that we are in fact in a downtrend
just created this lower low this lower
high and this lower low meaning that our
major swing level in this trend is where
where's the major swing low that was
just broken that would be this level
right here so for that reason what are
we going to do to see if this is a major
level of structure that we can trade
around we're going to place a horizontal
Zone in this area of structure we're
then going to scroll left and ask
ourselves is this area an area that has
been tested multiple times as support or
resistance that answer is yes so with
those criteria met I know that this Zone
this Zone that we have pointed out is in
fact a major resistance level it's my
major structure level that I want to
look for trading opportunities in to
which direction if we're in a downtrend
and we're trading Trend continuation I'm
looking in this area for possible sell
trades for the market to continue in
this downtrend from this area of major
structure if I click play you'll see
that eventually price does make it to
that area and eventually price does in
fact continue in that downtrend next up
let's talk about reversal major levels
of structure so in this case we're in a
downtrend here on the Euros Swiss what
is the major swing low and major swing
High we need to point out in order to
determine if we have a reversal out of
this Market well hopefully you remember
this from the reversal section of the
video but the level we want to see
broken is the previous high of the
previous pullback if that level is in
fact broken then we have evidence that
this Market could be reversing so in
this situation what we would need to see
for that evidence is price to push up
and close Above This previous major
swing High which was the previous
pullback in our downtrend now the way we
actually spot out the zone for this is
by doing a very similar thing that we do
for train continuation zones we want to
look at this level we want to put a line
or create a zone out of this level and
then we want to look left and see if
that has been tested multiple times now
what I mean by this is now since we do
see that this level has been tested
multiple times we know it's a major
level of structure for a reversal
opportunity I'm not going to be looking
here for possible sell trades that may
work but that's just not how I trade
Trend continuation what I would rather
see in this specific scenario is I want
to see price break and close Above This
level and then I'm going to be looking
in that zone in that level for possible
buy trades because of the anticipation
of a reversal based on our Trend and
reversal analysis we've already done so
let's click blade so as you can see
price does in fact close above our
previous major swing High here and I'm
going to adjust the Zone a little bit
now that we've created another little
level of structure right here and with
that being the case the Zone looks a
little more like this now and let's go
ahead and see what price does if we push
forward a bit we get back into this Zone
on the very next candle and eventually
after doing so price does in fact
reverse to the upside and give a major
move in the upwards Direction here we
have an example of a bearish reversal
hopefully you've already figured out why
but let me go ahead and explain this so
we have our uptrend here pushing higher
into new structure highs new structure
lows new structure highs what has just
happened our reversal scenario has just
happened by Price breaking and closing
below our previous major swing low or
the previous pullback for this uptrend
once that break and close below happens
that's when I'm actually Drawing the
Line to point out my major structure
level in this reversal scenario the
where do I want to place this trade I
know we're in a reversal scenario I know
there's evidence that we can see this
uptrend disappear and we can see the
start of a new downtrend with that being
the case I want to know where the most
profitable and the most accurate area
for me to place a trade in is going to
be and that's where this major structure
level comes in again we want to point
out a Zone utilizing that previous swing
low that was broken we want to turn it
into a Zone and ask ourselves has it
been tested multiple times looking left
if the answer to those questions is yes
then we have again a major level of
structure and in this case a major level
of structure to look for possible short
trades in based on the fact that we have
evidence of a reversal from our previous
uptrend that could turn this Market into
not enough Trend anymore but now a
downtrend and that's where we're going
to catch those profits is by looking for
trades in this area in anticipation for
that new downtrend to start now there is
actually one more thing we can add to
our price action trading to make it even
more accurate and that's what we're
talking about in the next lesson so
let's go ahead and move on
[Music]
now so utilizing higher time frame
analysis is actually very simple but
it's also optional what you've learned
so far works even if you're only trading
on one time frame but if you really want
to step up the accuracy of your price
action trading then trading utilizing
higher time frame analysis is going to
be the way to do that so let's go ahead
and talk about how simple utilizing
higher time frame analysis really is the
only thing you have to do to utilize
higher time frame analysis in your
trading when it comes to price action at
least for the way I utilize it in my
trading is to go up one time frame from
your trading time frame or in other
words the time frame you plan to place
the trade on go up one time frame and do
the exact analysis you've already
learned throughout this video so what I
mean by that is if you were someone who
wanted to trade on the F minute chart
you would do your Trend SL reversal and
major structure level analysis all on
the 15 minute so you'd look on the 15
minute to see if we're in an uptrend A
downtrend or preparing for some type of
reversal you would also spot out your
major levels of structure on the
15-minute time frame and then you would
go down to the 5minute time frame to
place an entry now we're going to talk
about entries in the next couple of
sections in this video but this is all
you have to do in order to implement
higher time frame analysis into your
price action trading so just to make
sure you have a handle on this if you
were trading the 15-minute chart where
would you be looking for things like
Trend or reversal scenarios and your
major levels of structure you would be
looking for those on the 1our chart if
you were trading the 1 hour you'd
obviously be looking at the 4H hour
chart for those things and if you're
trading the 4 Hour you would be looking
at the daily chart for Trends structure
levels and possible reversals now I know
that this is an extremely simple concept
but to ensure everyone's on the same
page let me go through one example with
you here we are on the Aussie New
Zealand daily chart we're on the daily
chart we've looked to find our Trend
which is what in this case we have a
push up that broke Above This previous
swing high that also was then broken
above once more so at this point we're
not just in a reversal we've actually
started a new uptrend so since we're in
an uptrend what's our level we're going
to be looking at for possible trades
inside of it's going to be that previous
major swing High we also have to look
left here on the daily chart to ensure
that that level has in fact been tested
multiple times since that is all the
case here on the daily chart utilizing
multiple time frames just means I'm
going down one time frame 2our 4our
chart and this is where I'm looking for
my possible rentes I'm waiting on the
4our chart at this point for price to
get into this Zone I created on the
daily chart and give me an entry reason
show me buying pressure in this area to
insinuate that we are looking at Trend
continuation out on the daily chart but
we're getting involved with entry stops
and targets down here on the 4our chart
and so again with this higher time frame
analysis we're just looking one time
frame above our trading time frame for
all the analysis you've already learned
throughout the entire video then
dropping down one time frame to our
trading time frame to look for the entry
to place our stops and to place our
targets so now that you understand Trend
and reversing markets to give us the
direction we want to trade in now that
you understand major levels of structure
to tell us where we want to be looking
for those trades at and now that you
understand how to add a little more
accuracy with higher time frame analysis
the next question we have to ask is how
do we actually enter the trade and
that's what we're going to talk about in
the next lessons so let's go ahead and
move
[Music]
on so Candlestick patterns are something
I use every single day in my own trading
and the reason for that is a Candlestick
pattern is going to show you a clear
sign of buying or selling pressure
depending on if you want to go long or
go short and it gives you a completely
objective way of entering into a trade I
love both of those things so for that
reason I love Candlestick patterns and
the ones I'm going to be teaching you
are the on that I utilize in 90% of the
trades I take based on Candlestick
patterns you're about to learn two
Candlestick patterns I have found to
perform the best in my own 10-year
trading career let's go ahead and Jump
Right In now I understand this may be
review for a lot of you but for those of
you brand new or those of you that don't
know what this Candlestick pattern is I
want to go over some quick examples of
it the first Candlestick pattern you're
going to be learning is the engulfing
Candlestick pattern we're going to start
off with a bullish engulfing pattern
which is an extremely simple pattern all
it is is is a red candle followed by a
green candle and the green candle has a
larger body than the previous red candle
if that is the case we have a bullish
engulfing candle again extremely simple
you should be able to spot these very
objectively with no confusion about
whether or not you have an engulfing
candle and what this candle shows us is
buying pressure we had a previous red
candle that was completely eclipsed by
our buyers on the very next candle
this shows us aggressive buying pressure
in this area which can often lead to a
push higher now just to be clear on how
I would utilize this in my trading we're
on that same aie New Zealand right now
the a New Zealand is right here we've
already looked at the trend we've
already found our area that we're
looking for possible trades in we're
utilizing higher time frame analysis
then we're doing this on the daily chart
I would be dropping down to the 4 Hour I
would be waiting for price to get into
this Zone I would then be waiting for
that engulfing Candlestick pattern to
occur and that Candlestick pattern would
be my entry now Candlestick patterns are
a more aggressive form of entering the
market that I utilize I like to utilize
these patterns in what I consider
perfect scenarios so this would be an
aggressive way to enter a trade after
all of your analysis is already done
you've already found the trend you've
already determined whether or not the
Market's reversing you've already found
your major level of structure can sck
patterns by themselves are not going to
make you profitable but when you add
them to all the other things you've
learned in this video they have proven
to be a profitable way of trading for me
now let's take a look at a bearish
engulfing candle so in this scenario we
have prices pushing lower we have a new
lower high this creates our new lower
low what are we looking at next we're
going to try to find that major level of
structure on this example we're just
going to utilize one time frame no
higher time frame analysis here is our
area of structure and if we scroll left
we can see that it has in fact been
tested multiple times so what this is
telling us is we're in a downtrend and
we have a major level of structure right
here in this area is where I would look
for a more aggressive entry if that's
something I decided to do and the way I
would be looking for that is by looking
for a bearish engulfing candle and you
can see that candle right here so for a
bearish engulfing candle we're looking
for a green candle followed by a red
candle and the red candle has a larger
body than the previous green candle that
is a bearish engulfing candle and what
this candle signifies is selling
pressure we had buyers really trying to
take control on this last candle then
buyers pushed up a little higher with
this Wick followed by sellers taking
complete control and closing all the way
down here creating that engulfing
Candlestick pattern and what this
pattern indicates is that sellers could
be taking back control in our overall
downtrend and that we can see prices
start to push lower from here which is
exactly what we see happen here on the
Aussie New Zealand the next Candlestick
pattern you're going to learn is the
hammer and shooting star Candlestick
patterns these Candlestick patterns are
super simple as well and I have a very
specific way that I personally spot them
to keep things as objective as possible
what I do is when I see a Candlestick
that looks like a hammer candle which is
this by the way a hammer candle is
normally going to be a candle with a
long Wick to the bottom side and with
the entire body of the candle in the top
1/3 of that entire Candlestick so what I
mean by that is from the low of the
candle to the top of the candle the high
of the Candlestick itself the body
normally needs to be in the top third I
have a very easy way that I spot this
personally and that is by utilizing a
Fibonacci retracement I just take the
Fibonacci retracement from the lowest
point of the candle up to the highest
point of the candle and as long as the
entire body of this candle is above the
38.2% retracement then I classifi this
as a hammer candle so that is how simple
it is to spot Hammer candles any candle
that meets that criteria for me is a
hammer Candlestick if you want to copy
my Fibonacci settings right here they
are just to have the same exact setup I
do and if you use Fibonacci in your
trading outside of this you may not want
to do that but this is the only way I
use Fibonacci in my own trading is to
spot these patterns so that is a hammer
Candlestick and the way I would utilize
this is if we look left here what do we
have on price action what has price done
based on our Trend and reversal analysis
well we have prices pushing lower new
lower high new lower low and then what
then we have a breaking close above our
previous major swing High what does this
tell us the downtrend could be over and
we could be looking at a possible
uptrend here on the New Zealand Yen the
next thing we do is spot out our
previous level of structure by asking
ourselves has that swing High been
tested multiple times in in the past the
answer to that is yes so once we get
down to this level if I'm looking to
enter this trade in a more aggressive
way then I may decide to do so with this
Hammer Candlestick pattern now something
that adds a little more accuracy to this
is to wait for a green candle after it
this is just something you have to
decide though because if you wait for
that green candle you may miss a few
opportunities and although it's a little
more accurate to do so you're going to
have fewer trades but if you do wait for
that green candle your trades are going
to be slightly more ACC accurate but
these Candlestick patterns essentially
represent a full candle where sellers
tried to take control and push prices
down but buyers said no took back
control and pushed prices all the way
back up to the top oneir of this entire
candle and that obviously signifies
buying pressure and that buying pressure
along with all the other analysis can
signal that we're going to see a big
push to the upside just like we saw here
on the New Zealand Yen on the screen in
front of you prices what type of trend
based on our Trend analysis we can tell
this is a downtrend because of this one
two three move if we're in a downtrend
and we're looking for a major level of
structure what do we do we take a look
at the previous swing low that was
broken right here and we look left to
see if that area has in fact been tested
multiple times as we can see here that
area has been tested multiple times here
on the pound New Zealand after that is
when I would look for these Candlestick
patterns in the this zone so what we're
going to do is push price forward a bit
as you can see we're now in this Zone
and it may be a little hard to see but
what do we get right here this would be
a shooting star candle and the reason is
for a shooting star candle the way I
objectively identify these candlesticks
is by pulling a Fibonacci retracement
from the very top of that candle the
highest point of the wig to the very
bottom of that candle the lowest point
of the wig and as long as the body
exists below the 38.2% retracement I
have what I consider a shooting star
candle now those are the rules for the
shooting star candle and what this
candle indicates is quite the opposite
of a hammer this candle indicates buyers
trying to take control all the way up to
the top of this Wick but within the same
exact candle sellers said no pushing
prices all the way back down again to
the bottom thirds of this entire
Candlestick pattern that creates our
shooting star and again these indicate
possible selling pressure when we
combine that with our already being in a
downtrend and we combine that with
spotting a major level of structure and
waiting patiently for price to get to
that level we can often times see prices
push lower after that shooting star
candle as you can see here the trend
continuation of that previous downtrend
so those are my two favorite Candlestick
patterns and again I use Candlestick
patterns like these to enter in a more
aggressive way but what if I want to
take a more conservative approach to
entering the market inside of one of
these zones that's what you're going to
learn next let's go ahead and take a
look at the next section
[Music]
now chart patterns are another one of my
favorite ways to enter into trades I use
them for a more conservative and a
slightly more accurate approach to
placing trades than Candlestick patterns
themselves chart patterns do provide
more accuracy but with that added
accuracy comes fewer trading
opportunities everything's a give and
take in trading so keep that in mind
when deciding what you want to trade but
right now what I want to do is go over
my favorite two chart patterns these
patterns account for 90% of the trades I
plac when utilizing chart patterns so
let's dive into them right now the first
chart pattern you're going to learn is
the double bottom chart pattern now as
with candlestick patterns these chart
patterns are only applicable after all
of the other analysis is done that we've
talked about so we're going to say that
all that analysis is done we're going to
say this is our major level of support
what I mean by that is we're looking for
buying opportunities from this Zone
based on all of our other analysis with
that being the case let me explain the
exact rules I utilize when trading
double bottoms so when trading double
bottoms I wait for our first bottom of
the double bottom I wait for a pullback
and at the point that I start to see
this pullback I actually create a Zone
utilizing that first bottom and the way
I do that this Zone exists between the
bottom of the bodies of that first leg
of the double bottom all the way down to
the lowest Wick of this first leg of the
double Bottom now with this being the
case I call this our termination Zone
what that means is price must come down
and at least touch this area with a wick
price can come all the way down and
close inside of this area a wick can go
past this area the only thing I cannot
see is price close below this area and
as long as that's the case then I have a
valid double bottom what I mean by that
is if we get a close below like this
awkwardly drawn candle we have on the
screen now that's going to indicate what
that close below indicates Trend
continuation to the downside so I don't
want to look at that as a double bottom
but as long as that does not happen and
as long as we do in fact get at least
the touch of this zone I'm considering
that a double bottom let me go a little
further here once we do this I consider
this a double bottom but I do not place
a trade just because I have this valid
double bottom here the only time I place
a trade is when I see buying pressure
after the second leg of this double
bottom so this would be considered the
second bottom of our double bottom and
what I want to see is after the touch of
our termination Zone that we see buying
pressure before we see a close below the
wick of our previous swing low so at
this point what am I waiting on I'm
waiting for buying pressure now I count
buying pressure as a significant green
candle or as a hammer candle so next up
that's what I want to see once I see
that my rules are met to actually place
an entry at this point is when I would
place the actual entry I would place a
stop loss below the lowest swing low of
the double bottom I have different ways
that I take targets but for this example
we're going to go with a 1.4 to1 reward
to risk ratio and that would be the ACT
ual trade setup so to briefly go over
that one more time when I see this first
bottom I create a zone between the body
and the lowest low of that first bottom
once we start to see a pullback I want
to see in order to classify this as a
double bottom prices pull back enough to
at least touch this Zone again a body
closing inside this zone is fine and if
we see a wick go past this Zone that's
completely fine all of that still
indicates that we have a double bottom
the only thing I don't want to see is a
close below the wick of that first
bottom and as long as we don't have that
after we touch the termination Zone and
we see buying pressure like this candle
here that's when I'm okay placing the
trade based on this double bottom again
after all the other analysis that we've
talked about so far in this video is all
met after all of that is when I want to
see this exact double bottom setup and
what these double bottoms do is indicate
obvious buying pressure ESP especially
when you add that you want to see buying
pressure after the second bottom as
you'll see here this can often lead to a
rise in price and major push to the
upside the next chart pattern we're
going to take a look at is a double top
now this is the same exact thing just
flipped upside down I utilize the same
exact rules so for a double top in this
case we're going to pretend that this is
our major level of structure and that
we're trading a trend continuation trade
and now we have our first top followed
by a pull back once this pullback starts
to happen I'm going to be creating a
Zone with a box from the bodies to the
top of the wick of that first top this
is what we call the termination Zone and
in this zone is where I want a candle to
at least touch but not close above if I
get a close Above This Zone that
signifies Trend continuation I don't
want to be a part of that trying to sell
after the market tells me Trend
continuation is likely so if that
happens I'm not interested in a double
top trade but if we get a candle that
closes in this area if we get a wick
that touches this area or even if we get
a wick that goes beyond this area all of
that is still valid for a double top
trade as we push price forward a bit you
can see that we do in fact touch our
termination Zone with this candle now
this candle also happens to be what this
is a shooting star candle so what this
is showing me is not only a double top
but now this is showing me a double top
with selling pressure at the second top
so this would be my actual reason for
entering these trades again I'm not just
utilizing the double top itself I want
to see selling pressure at that second
top stops the same way above the
previous swing high and for these
examples we're going to do a 1.4 to1
reward to risk ratio after we get that
double top and we see selling pressure
and again we've already done all of our
previous analysis that showed us we were
inside of a major level of structure
that double top can now indicate
that prices are likely to fall and that
we could see a major push to the
downside so those are my two favorite
chart patterns they are double tops and
double bottoms and those are my exact
rules for how I actually Place trades
utilizing those two patterns let's move
on to the next section of the video
right
[Music]
now now we're going to take everything
you've learned so far in this video and
combine it into an entire price action
trading system you can use utilize to
pull profits out of the market we're
going to do so by taking a look at a
dollar Canada trade I had last week I
put a clip of that trade running live on
the screen so you can see that I
actually did place it and this trade was
taken based on the exact price action
trading system you've been learning
throughout this video so let's go ahead
and break this trade down and create a
full trading plan around the price
action skills you've learned throughout
this entire video here we are taking a
look at the dollar Canada chart and
based on the trend and reversal analysis
that you've learned how how to do so far
in the video what would you say is
happening right now on the dollar Canada
based on price action well here on this
chart we can see that we had an uptrend
as the market was continuously making
new higher highs and higher lows and
what has recently happened what recently
has happened is price has pushed down
breaking below the most recent pullback
of our uptrend or our most recent major
swing low when this happens what does
that tell us that tells us that the
market is primed for a possible reversal
so if we're looking at this as a
possible reversing situation what's the
next step the next step is to make a
Zone where that previous swing low is
and ask ourselves is it a major level of
structure we do that by looking left to
see if that zone has in fact been tested
multiple times and that answer is yes if
we look left here you can see that we
have another test of resistance here
here and here along with a little test
of resistance right before that swing
low so with that being the case we not
only have our reversing situation but we
also have our major level of structure
point it out and this is where we're
going to look for those opportunities
remember the trend in reversal analysis
gives us the direction we want to trade
we're looking for short trades because
of the reversal the major level of
structure shows us where we want to
trade and our Candlestick SL chart
patterns shows us how we're going to
enter into the market into in this case
that sell position so what we're waiting
on now is a pullback to this area
followed by either an aggressive entry
if that's the way you decide to trade in
a more aggressive way which would be a
Candlestick pattern that we've discussed
in this video or a more conservative
entry like a double top in this area
let's push price forward and see what we
got last week right here what do you
notice does this Candlestick pattern
look familiar hopefully you said yes
this is the exact rules we have for an
engulfing candle and this is actually
exactly when I decided to place this
trade so with all of our price action
analysis already done and then seeing
this Candlestick pattern I decided to
enter aggressively on this trade and
when it comes to a stop loss I always go
above this swing high but if I can also
get that stop loss above the Zone I've
created then that's always a plus so in
this case I went just above the zone and
I had my first Target set at a 1.4 to1
reward to risk ratio and as we push
forward you will see that this did in
fact come down far enough to hit those
first targets at a 1. 4:1 reward to risk
ratio not only did I take this trade in
my own account this was also a trade I
sent to all the students we have
involved in the TTC Forex University
they receive analysis like this two to
five times every single week based on
the trades I'm actually taking to show
them how I'm placing trades in real
markets and in real time not only that
the university is essentially an entire
trading course talking you all the way
through the complete Basics to extremely
Advanced Techniques and strategies you
can utilize to pull profits out of the
market and on top of that it is a
mentorship program meaning that anytime
you have trading related questions I
will personally be there to answer those
questions for you through email to
ensure that your journey to profitable
trading is as smooth as possible so if
you want to get all the details to the
TTC Forex University just click the top
Link in the description of this video or
go to www. thetradingcarder
frame trading plan as I said this system
works whether you use it on a single
time frame or utilize higher time frames
to add accuracy let's walk through the
higher time frame trade plan right now
so as you can see the first step in our
trading plan is to identify the
conditions of the market the way we're
going to do this on the higher time
frame which is going to be one time
frame above whatever time frame you're
trading on is we're going to identify
whether the market is in a trending or
reversing Market structure in the same
way you've learned how to do throughout
this video the second step of the
strategy to make sure the market is
pulling back to a major level of
structure so you'll be identifying that
major level of structure the way you've
learned in this video and you'll wait
patiently for price to get into that
area because you know that's the most
accurate area to trade from while either
trading with the trend of the market or
with the possible reversal after that
we're going to be dropping down to your
actual trading time frame to look for
possible entries the entries are going
to be if you want to enter in a more
aggressive style utilizing Candlestick
patterns like the engulf in pattern or
38.2% candle that you've learned
throughout this video the 38.2% candle
again is just either a hammer or
shooting star I just call them that
because of the way I identify them with
the Fibonacci retracement next up if
you're looking for a more conservative
reason for entry then you're going to be
looking for chart patterns like double
tops and double Bottoms in that area
with the added buying or selling
pressure after the double top or bottom
after we have our conditions and entries
we then then move on to stops and
targets these are very important as well
for stops we always want to go above or
below the swing high or low that was
created by the Candlestick pattern or
that was created by the chart pattern if
we can get above or below the zone of
structure we've created that is always a
good thing as well and for targets what
I would suggest for anyone who is a
beginner is to utilize fixed targets
between a 1.4 to1 and a 2:1 reward to
risk ratio so I'll go ahead and delete
all of my drawings if you feel like
screenshotting this so that you can have
it on a Google doc or even have it
printed out beside your desk that way
you know every rule you need to follow
in order to follow this price action
trading plan now though I'm going to
move on and we're going to talk about
the single time frame trade plan for
this price Action System the single time
frame price action trading plan is
exactly the same except we're not
switching time frames so I don't feel
like I need to go over that again
instead I want to put this here just in
case yet again you're going to be
utilizing a single time frame trading
plan and you want to take a screen
screenshot so feel free to do that now
so with that being the case you now have
a complete price action trading plan
that you can use to practice with you
can back test and you can decide whether
or not you want to implement this as
another trading strategy in your trading
Arsenal this system is something that
has helped me pull profits out of the
market for over the past eight years and
I really hope that it can do the same
thing for you don't forget if you're
interested in the TTC Forex University
our mentorship program go ahead and
click the top Link in the description or
go to www.th trading channel.com if
you're not interested in that no big
deal at all just be sure that you're
subscribed here and click the
notification Bell so you're alerted when
we come out with more valuable content
click that like button comment if you
made it to the end and I will like every
comment that says they made it to the
end I hope you trade green best of luck
in the markets and I'll talk to you in
the next video see you soon